hey folks Brett here welcome to the
first official episode of Brett
Weinstein's Dark Horse podcast I am
sitting with an Dino who is a sub editor
at Colette magazine who has been
documenting protests in the streets of
Portland
since 2016 Andi became extraordinarily
well known in the last two days as a
result of an attack that took place on
the streets of Portland as he was
reporting on an taifa Andy welcome to
the podcast thank you for having me on
so you've had quite an extraordinary run
over the last several days do you want
to tell us roughly what happened yeah
it's probably not every day that a
podcast guest comes in with a beat up
face like mine what happened was on the
29th of June I was documenting a
demonstration organized by antiphon
Portland Portland for your listeners who
may not be aware as a progressive
monoculture and it has a very large
movement of far less radicals who call
themselves anti-fascist and they
organize under that name and they were
there to oppose frightening groups so I
came with my GoPro and steps away from
the Mahnomen County Justice Center one
of the most important institutions of
the rule of law in Portland because it
houses courthouses the sheriff's office
the central police precinct when they
were marching there chanting no hate no
fear the next thing that I that happened
to me was I got hit in the back of the
head really hard and I'm an extremely
possible person I've never been in a
fight so I don't even until now didn't
know what a punch felt like so it took a
few seconds for me to register what had
happened I was knocked forward
by the time I realized it and kind of
regain my balance the punches and hits
just kept coming and from every
direction and when I thought it was over
it wasn't let's back up a little bit you
and I are friends and I'm also a Twitter
follower of yours and you were quite
concerned about what would happen to you
at this protest and you and I talked
about whether I might join you
ultimately I did not join you I am
pretty recognizable and the anti if is
not a fan of me and I suspect had I been
there it would have just created a
second victim but nonetheless you knew
that these folks had the potential for
violence and you went anyway why did you
go you're right that I've been targeted
quite relentlessly by Anti Fog
particularly since the 1st of May Mayday
that was when I was maced and punched in
the stomach and then docks they released
my family's address online and then a
few days after that attacked when I was
at the gym all of these incidents were
reported to police in not much action
had been done names of suspects provided
but no arrests made more than two months
ago so I knew what I thought I was going
into a hostile environment and I knew
that the attacks on me before were meant
to intimidate me until not documenting
them anymore
I think that's a key point is that the
purpose of the attacks is to ensure that
nobody documents what is taking place in
other words you have people the anti
foul who dress in black I think they
would probably say that they do it for
self protection but it's clearly a
mechanism to anonymize themselves so
that they can commit crimes and
get away with it so you have a group of
people who are massing dressed for
criminal activity and they don't want to
document it and so I guess what I'd like
to find out from you is what what was
your mindset at the point that you
decided to you know I mean it's quite
clear in the video that you walked not
only not only did you go to the protest
but you walked right into the ante for
ranks looking back now I feel naive but
I was thinking that if these people
really knew who I was they wouldn't
believe all the things that some of
their most devout ideologues were saying
about me for examples calling me a white
supremacist far-right a propagandist for
Nazis actually that morning before I
went to the event I put on a helmet
because of the escalating tensions I've
been happening and I caught a glimpse of
myself in the mirror before I left and I
decided to take the helmet off and leave
it at home I told myself I don't want to
give anybody even the possible
perception that I came ready to fight or
that on the hostile person I was a
mistake
[Music]
they went for my head and face and eyes
in the attack with weaponized gloves yes
from what I could see before I was
blinded by what they say when milkshakes
and eggs the the people punching me were
wearing gloves that have fiberglass
material on the knuckles so they're much
harder I believe that's probably what
caused the the cuts and abrasions when
the punches started happening all around
me
I kept thinking you know I could see the
org and justice the Mahnomen County
Justice Center I was thinking okay at
any moment the police are gonna come in
and swoop me out but it didn't happen
what ended up happening next was they
beat me so badly that I lost control of
my GoPro which was brand-new and I that
was the one thing I was looking forward
to a lot was using it for the first time
a mouse person grabbed it away from me
and ran off and then I thought okay they
have that do they have what they want
and they're gonna leave me alone now
I put up my arms to block my face from
any more hits and to also say signal to
them that this is a surrender they took
that as a sign to go in harder so then
came more punches more kicks and a hail
of liquids blinded me really stung my
skin and they sprayed stuff all over me
and so when I was walking away that you
may have seen in the viral video now I
was just hoping that I was walking in no
direction away from them because I
actually didn't know where I was going
you know as I just kept walking walking
and I said at any minute now the police
are gonna run in and help me and it
never happened I made it all the way
across the park to the the front of the
courthouse and I lost my balance and I
sat on the ground and a SWAT team of
medics approached me I let them know
that I needed help they said in order to
get to the ambulance and be taken to the
hospital I needed to walk back to the
police precinct so I had to go back in
the direction of where I was just
attacked by above this crowd so the
police were there they were nearby
they were nearby and they did not act
they didn't so there are a couple things
that I think need to be interjected here
you say they punched you I think it has
to be made clear to the audience they
sucker-punched you there was no question
that you were not going to hit back
it would have been insane to do so and
it isn't your nature and they well know
that they sucker-punched you wearing
disguises to get away with it
they used weaponized gloves so even a
punch doesn't capture what happened to
you
the injuries on your face do but this
was an attack by cowards of somebody who
they knew would not fight back and I
must say I find that absolutely
despicable and I think that something
also needs to be said with respect to
your presence there which is I feel you
know when I heard that you had been
injured and I knew that you had worried
that it might happen I sort of I
couldn't help but draw a connection with
Christopher Hitchens having elected to
be waterboarded in order to discover if
it was torture you know it's not a
perfect analogy but in a sense who wants
to be waterboarded right but somebody
has to in order to be able to speak with
authority about what it is who wants to
be attacked by the anti feh
nobody but to the extent that they want
to pretend that what they are doing is
fighting fascists somebody has to
document their fight and the fact that
that puts you in danger is the point how
is it possible that somebody like you
going into a protest with a camera is
attacked with police nearby and they
don't intervene that tells you something
is very wrong with the system and it is
wrong in particular here in Portland and
I think the reason has a lot to do with
the mayor the mayor who also in this
case happens to be the police
commissioner and I can't help but point
out the connection between what happened
here to you and what happened in
Evergreen
to me the president of evergreen college
happens to be in a position to tell the
police not to intervene in criminal
activity because the campus police are
the ones with jurisdiction and he
happens to be their boss it happens to
be the case in Portland that the mayor
is also the police commissioner and if
there's one lesson that is absolutely
clear from what happened over the
weekend it's that you can't have a mayor
who has to face re-election in charge of
deciding whether or not the police
enforced the law because what will
happen is that a mayor pandering to a
particular constituency will end up
putting people in danger I know that I
have a family here and I feel in danger
living in Portland knowing that the
mayor will not enforce the law if
certain people are committing crimes but
not others and I think somehow this just
has to has to end the police have to
enforce the law yeah an tyfa are very
clear that they have no respect for it
they chant all cops are bastards right
out in the open and then they commit
crimes it needs to be addressed the
police and authorities had ample
opportunity to prepare properly for
Saturday because anti-fur had
broadcasted their intent to
quote-unquote
physically confront and with the group's
long history of militant violence I
don't understand why the police keep
responding the same way which is
basically just to let citizens be
assaulted with impunity I mean being in
front of you today I'm speaking a little
bit slower from those injuries that day
to my head the CT scan at the hospital
confirm that I have a brain hemorrhage
and I've never had a brain injury and
it's only now the more that I'm speaking
that I'm realizing oh there's certain
minor deficiencies that I didn't realize
while just laying in the hospital bed
right so you're actually feeling some
sort of neurological deficit from brain
injury I do and it sounds it makes the
sound like so serious and at the time I
know that I was bleeding and dazed and
all that but like I said I'd never been
in a fight so I thought maybe wasn't as
bad that's what happened then I watched
this video and there's at least a dozen
people just kicking hitting throwing
stuff at me and then I see oh it was
that bad no it was absolutely that bad I
mean you were not only admitted to the
hospital but visited you in the hospital
I heard them give the orders that you
had to be awakened every hour to make
sure you didn't fall into a coma this
was this was serious stuff you were you
received a serious head injury at the
hands of people who are role playing
some kind of bizarre delusion that
fascists are everywhere that you are one
and this it just can't be and I must say
when I when I went to the hospital I was
expecting that I wasn't even sure they
were gonna let me in I was expecting the
press to be descending on you in some
form and when I got there you know I was
surprised that you were in the hallway
right he hadn't gotten a room yet you
know I mean it was true that they
required you to leave your name to go
visit you but am i right that the press
is largely so far not covered the story
it's unfortunate that some stories have
been focused on how the write bounced
on this in took advantage of this story
for their own cause rather than focusing
on not just what happened to me but the
larger context of political violence
that have been escalating in the city
ever since the 2016 election results
were announced so there's a lot to be
learned from this
I think the parallels between what
happened to you and what happened to me
at Evergreen are too many to ignore and
there is a way in which I know that the
right did I wouldn't say pounced on the
story but there's a way in which this
story matches an accusation that the
right has been leveling but that was
exactly the same thing that happened
when it was me in their sights and I'm
not on the right so I see this as very
much a non partisan issue
you have people who say that they are on
the Left behaving very illiberal e
behaving violently and responding to an
unknown stand delusional view of what's
taking place in society and the things
that are supposed to kick in and prevent
it from happening are not functioning
for political reasons so you have a
sense of what should happen next so that
this doesn't happen to somebody else
the local authorities need to heed the
warnings of the federal authorities when
it comes to antiva
in 2000 Stu thousand 16 the DHS has
described anti-fur activities as
domestic terrorist violence not the
group itself from the movements off but
the activities and that is something
that the local police hear either for
political reasons or what I don't know
don't take serious
in fact unfortunately very recently the
Portland City Council actually voted to
withdrawal the city from that FBI Joint
Terrorism Task Force citing concerns
that the FBI and federal authorities
unfairly monitor Muslims and left-wing
groups so we have a City Council an
existing Xuan C in the city who are not
violent militants but share a certain
ideological alignments with an tyfa and
therefore believe their cause is just
immoral and this is what gives them the
legitimacy to continue to do what they
do they have a very there's a much
larger concentric circle of anti fuss
sympathetic writers in the media who
whitewash mainstream antiph attacked ex
into making it so the public don't even
see what they do was problematic but i
hope with what happened to me and i was
very fortunate that an Oregonian
journalist at least caught part of the
attack on camera that it brings to makes
it very clear that this movement does
not deserve to be called anti fascist
that's a absolute that's a misnomer that
they give themselves in the media has
been compliant in calling them that i've
been looking into this movement for a
while and i would describe them as a
paramilitary like movement of extreme
anarchists and incontinence and the the
modus operandi is violence and
intimidation against their opponents and
if not violence then disinformation and
misinformation
pains to smear the reputations of their
opponents for example somebody like me
who's written for mainstream
publications and works for a centrist
magazine smearing me as a Nazi and
therefore fit to be targeted to be dogs
to be hit and in this case maybe even
almost nearly killed
so yeah beneath human dignity is is the
objective they paint you as beneath
human dignity and then they act
according yeah that was me very so clear
to me when when all this happened and
nobody came to help me as I was
stumbling away bleeding blinded I could
hear the people laughing at me behind me
it's caught here yeah yeah and well it's
so ironic is that moments before they
were chanting no hate no fear well there
is some sort of a let's put it this way
the the illiberal authoritarian Left
keeps resetting the bar of ironing
everything about it is ironic you know
including the name anti-fascist which I
agree is not what they are at all and
you know again this goes back to this
being a non partisan issue we have a
criminal enterprise operating in the
open with the tacit approval of the
political apparatus which holds the
police back from simply enforcing the
law and the result is totally
predictable
I would also describe them as a
paramilitary organization in fact in
thinking about this interview that was
exactly the term that came to mind and
what also comes to mind is the fact that
people across the political spectrum
have seen the same thing if you don't
encounter an tyfa
you don't know what they're about but
once you've encountered them it becomes
very clear so for
Chris Hedges who is like me quite far to
the left has also had serious problems
with black bloc anarchists because they
are hell-bent on violence in fact it
becomes a kind of excuse for violence is
the false portrayal of this enemy that
can only be confronted with these
tactics and in fact there's a whole
language that surrounds that they talk
about a diversity of tactics diversity
of tactics is a code for we are going to
support those who wish to be violent and
behave in a way that allows them to
disappear into the crowd and not to pay
any price for doing so and you know
who's on the other end of it it's you it
could easily be me it's Chris Hedges it
makes no sense for this to be tolerated
and it it has an absolutely chilling
effect on discourse the simple ability
to say what is there are people dressed
to commit crimes who walk the streets
openly commit violent acts and are able
to get away with it they're masters of
doublespeak it's it starts in the name
from one and it goes down to everything
else for example like you said the
diversity of tactics what that is really
code for right supporting others and
maybe even engaging in violent physical
confrontations another one they use is
self defense community self defense
that's and they don't mean it how people
understand it self-defense to them is
offensive absolution that is
premeditated so I want to chase down a
an issue that I think is at the heart of
how this whole system functions
surrounding an incident like the one
that happened to you there's a way in
which people's teams are encoded very
deeply in their psyches at the moment
these things are reinforced on social
media by the algorithms that cause you
to encounter things that flatter your
preconceptions and demonize those that
you perceive as different from you and
it results in people looking at an event
like what happened with you and instead
of looking at it for what it is you know
a transparent attack a violent attack on
somebody who is simply reporting simply
pointing a camera at something in an
American street in broad daylight that
what happens is people Intuit what
sources they are to pay attention to in
order to have sense made of this event
so the fact that you were on Fox News
with Tucker Carlson tonight The Wall
Street Journal released a very sober
editorial about what happened to you
it's not surprising that those two
sources were the first people to pick up
on the story at Evergreen it's the usual
suspects and the reason it works this
way is because those on the Left know
that they are supposed to discount
anything that comes across those
airwaves and so there's a way in which
you've got people on Twitter for example
blue checkmark folks from the left
saying the most vile stuff about how you
deserve this attack and it's like what
would you have had to do to deserve an
attack there's nothing short of you
actually having engaged in violence
against your attackers that would
justify it and yet you have people who
are presumably educated and hold down a
job speaking as if pointing a camera at
a protest could possibly justify a
physical beating it makes it makes no
sense but it has something to do with us
having been divided the press who hasn't
shown up are the press that people who
see themselves as on the left pay
attention to and the press that has
shown up is the the press that is is
watched by people
the right and so the point is how is it
that an tyfa and people at large in
portland could have such a wrong
understanding of who you are well there
are two narratives about you there's one
narrative on the right and there's one
narrative on the left I can attest as
your friend and somebody who's
interacted with you personally that the
narrative about you on the Left bears
very little resemblance to reality you
know it has a few superficial analogies
to your actual person but in terms of
you know you're of Vietnamese descent
you're gay that gets reported those are
facts but but what is said about you is
that you're a provocateur right and I
think the point is the question is which
story would you like to believe would
you like to believe that Andy no points
a camera at things and you can interpret
as well as anybody what the footage
means or would you like to believe that
you know and you know is trying to paint
a picture to to demonize kids who are
upset about real stuff and the point is
those two stories are they can't be
reconciled and one of them is just
simply a fiction but for people who
start by pursuing the story in one of
those sources they will come to the
conclusion that somehow you invited this
it's unfortunate that some of the
mainstream press reporting on this as
well as the local paper of record
Oregonian has really chosen to focus on
labels to fix to me right wing right
wing provocative right wing commentator
it's as if to me that those my views in
my professional work as a journalist is
irrelevant to the talk that happened to
me by sort of contextualizing
work that anti-fur hates a mine I almost
feel like the kind of in a subtle way
finding a justification for what
happened to me it's it was the same
thing similarly to after the Charlie
Hebdo attacks in 2015 by the jihadists
than those on the progressive life
started raising our points like well the
publication was provocative and the work
that they published was insulting to
Muslims and their prophet and I don't
see what purpose those points serve
other than in a way to say indirectly
that you kind of had it coming yeah this
idea that you had it coming
is it's I mean I can't think of another
term other than its vile right and of
what troubles me most about it is that
we're Americans and somehow that is not
carrying any weight with people people
view you and me as other and I would
contrast that you and I travel in
parallel circles there's a group of
people who isn't behaving this way
people who I mean when we have gathered
outside of the context of events when
we've been you know and at a meal
together everybody knows that you and I
are in different sides of the political
spectrum it's not a fundamental fact it
might be the basis for a conversation
why is it that you and I see an issue
differently but there's no sense that
the other person is less deserving of
the right to walk down the street safely
that's a preposterous notion and so I
guess the question really is what
fraction
of the public is actually still in touch
with that idea that your politics
actually have nothing to say about
whether or not what happened to you in
the streets of Portland is is a tragic
and frightening turn of events of course
it is a human being who was reporting
which is as close to a sacred American
right as there is was physically
attacked for having done so that is an
offense to every person who actually
cares about the ideals that the nation
was founded on there's no left or right
about that it's just simply despicable
just before this interview I encountered
a couple of instances where somebody had
actually forged headlines made it appear
that publications had reported that you
had faked your own attack now I must say
that when I looked at these things my
first thought was not that they were a
forgery my first thought was oh my
goodness how could these publications
possibly portray this I mean I know
because I went to the hospital I saw you
injured in the immediate aftermath of
this attack you didn't fake an attack
that caused a brain bleed that's an
that's an insane notion well turns out
these publications didn't say that you
did but people who apparently were given
no pause whatsoever by the damage done
to you made it even worse by viciously
portraying you as the cause of the
attack against you I'm not even sure
what to say what is what is that like to
have people add insult to injury by just
simply manufacturing a reason to blame
you entirely for something for which you
have no blame an sefa has no problem
engaging
in houses and disseminating hoaxes
they're particularly angry at me that
back in earlier this year I heard a
story from the New York Post where
investigated 15-plus allegations that
were being pushed out by an tyfa and
their allies in by allies i mean the
democratic socialists of america and
various other far-left movements and
groups in town with claims that LGBT
people were being targeted for beatings
robberies murders kidnappings on the
streets of Portland living here you
could not find a more LGBT accepting
place and hearing that these things were
happening and yet the no evidence was
put forth and so in the one incident
that was reported to police the
narrative that was put out on the
GoFundMe about being beat on the head by
transpose was bats that story was
entirely different from that documented
in the police report so they're very
angry that I wrote that piece and now
perhaps they think it's a joke or maybe
it's just them trying to engage in
another hoax they're putting out these
fake story news stories green shots that
I was involved in paying people I knew
to beat me out so that I could do a
fundraiser and get money off well first
of all that would be a criminal act of
fraud so if anybody has any evidence of
wrongdoing in my part
make it public please
I see accusations that I was provoking
people and I would like specifics there
were cameras everywhere about activists
if you have evidence that I was not
conducting myself in a professional way
please put that out for the REC
I maintain that I was entirely
professional throughout the whole day
leading it up to and after the attack I
can also say that I've been at a protest
with you before I've seen the video of
how you behaved here there is a question
about the wisdom of walking into such a
scenario but it's the same question that
one would have to ask a war
correspondent is it smart to go to a war
zone well no it's not on the other hand
somebody has to do it and I think the
real point about the the wounds on your
face and the the injury to your head
that's a warning to the rest of us
that's a warning don't do what Andy does
and what Andy does is he points a camera
at things that other people don't he
reveals something true and those who are
participating in that true thing do not
wish it to be understood they wish to
portray themselves as the champion of
victims when in fact they are eager to
engage in violence and looking for an
excuse and willing to sucker-punch and
you know as far as I'm concerned you
don't need to defend yourself
from accusations that you had a hand in
this I appreciate your willingness to
invite people to present that evidence
and you know might that would be my
instinct too if I were in your shoes but
you didn't fake this attack you went to
a place where people involved in in
madness did what they do to witches and
the fact is that's all of our business
it is it is absolutely a threat to
decent people in Portland I wonder you
know have I moved to a town where I
can't be safe because the political
winds do not allow the law to be
enforced against people if they just
simply claim themselves to be on the far
left I mean that that can't be but maybe
that's maybe that's where we've landed
if I can add one more thing I do think
responsibility for this falls to mayor
wheeler I think that's the reason that
the police don't act it's not that the
police are confused about what needs to
happen and I would invite mayor wheeler
to come here I would be happy to talk to
him about what happened in your case I
would give him a fair shake although I
think he has a lot to answer for him but
I think the biggest question is we've
now seen the result of the mayor's
policy and that result is unacceptable
and is it going to take a death is that
what it's going to take in order for
something to be done or can can the
mayor read the obvious implication of
this attack which is the law has to be
enforced against all parties
irrespective of their political beliefs
and claims and that's just simply the
nature of a civilized society I want to
point out for the record that two
neighboring counties to Portland have
made the decision that they're no longer
going to assist a Portland Police Bureau
by sending their officers and they
mentioned the danger that their own
officers can be put in as well as the
anti police climate in the city this was
made so clear to me back in February
when I attended a policing Town Hall
where the mayor was honored at the table
with the police chief chief Danielle
outlaw and there was a ton of antiva and
far-left activists who just swarmed this
meeting and they used their numbers to
bowling and it reminded me some ways of
those scenes we saw in Evergreen of the
the crowd screaming
and that anger in what should be an
orderly meeting and they were calling
for the police to be dismantled and
[Music]
telling the mayor to that he was too
much in support of the police against
so-called victimized communities so this
is a message that he's hearing from the
most vocal and angry people who
unfortunately are very good at
organizing particularly because they
have no problems with using
misinformation and disinformation and
with Portland being the monoculture that
it is there's really no counterpoise
providing a different not just even a
different perspective like setting the
facts around certain issues in the city
around policing for example it's all
about narratives and I wonder sometimes
if these people have taken on their
identity as anarchists or communists and
put themselves in aunty fuzz it seems
like they they have they lost meaning
and purpose in their life and so they're
looking for it through these extremist
ideologies and you know when it comes to
religious extremism fortunately that's
very easy to recognize when it comes to
far-right extremism what the public is
very good at and I would argue perhaps
overly sensitive at defining what that
is when it comes to the far left seems
to be no agreed on definition and even
when you
hasta la what does it look like for the
left to go too far they struggle to find
enough to give an answer yeah and you
know it's a it's an obvious loophole if
you just simply self define as acting on
behalf of marginalized people apparently
you're entitled to attack journalists in
the street and you know that can't be
it's just you you there can't be a
self-defined option to violate the law
to dress in such a way that you
anonymize yourself and it's obviously a
game from the point of view of most of
the ban tyfa and so let me ask you this
you're a journalist you work with
Colette and I'm wondering how one does
journalism in an environment that is
this polarized and toxic and in which
one side is entitled apparently to
commit violence to call an uphill battle
is an understatement
Colette being one of the few
publications of its reach that is
pushing back against this has come under
relentless attacks from very established
journalists accusing the magazine of
being reactionary alts right all right
all these things to deal Ajith my's it
and it's catching on a little bit in
some of the reporting he's again lies to
do legitimize your opponents and it's
about and I think this is an expression
either you or somebody else said but I
didn't come up with it but it's about
creating phantom enemies it's also about
preventing you from seeing with your own
eyes right there's something about
you know if you hear that colette is
fringe far-right whatever it may be
before you ever read a quill that
article then a you probably don't go
check it out if you don't view yourself
as right-of-center in other words what's
being broadcast is kind of a a stigma
that prevents people from looking any
farther it sounds sophisticated oh well
of course they would say that that's
Colette and they're known to be
reactionary well they're I wouldn't know
how to categorize Colette politically I
see stuff all across the map and in fact
that's what you want is a publication
where you can't quite peg where they are
because they're not ideological they're
actually exploring things and you know I
see stuff and Colette that causes me to
roll my eyes for sure
but I can't name the publication where
that isn't the case and I think the most
important point is the strategy that is
being deployed prevents readers from
engaging content they need to see and it
prevents reporters from actually getting
to the story because they can see a
threat that is all too real on your face
and you know I mean that's what this is
this is a threat to all who would expose
what's taking place and that threat is
strategically powerful
you know some people asked have asked me
you know how auntie fun hates you why
didn't you come more prepared and all
that I kept telling myself like I am
living and working in a major American
city I'm not in Afghanistan or Iraq I'm
not in a war zone why why do I need to
come with you know a balance of security
with a with helmets any of that now you
know I look and I say well unfortunately
there are days in Portland where it is
like a literal war zone Saturday was one
of them
and it's easy to dismiss what happened
as unremarkable as a local journalist
with ulema week described it that's it's
easy to have that view until what
happens to me happens to you then it's
not unremarkable
yeah it's not unremarkable at all it's
utterly remarkable and you know I had
the same response at the point during
the evergreen riots where I was being
literally hunted and the police told me
that they were actually powerless to do
anything about it because the President
had ordered them to stand down
my thought was this cannot possibly be
happening in the u.s. in what was then
2017 I'm being hunted in my own
neighborhood on my own campus in 2017
and the police can't do anything about
it like that's just it's an out of this
world kind of experience like what did I
fall off my timeline what happened and
you know I think if there is a saving
grace in what happened to you it's that
we all fell off our timelines together
we now
have seen this we will see the response
and if the response doesn't make any
sense then at least we will know where
we are the silver lining for me in this
is when I was in the hospital I didn't
think that this story would get big I
mean what snoozy about some guy getting
beat up happens all the time right I've
seen this outpouring of support and the
disgust that a lot of people have I mean
there was a lot of people took Glee but
fortunately more people took discusses
what happened I hope that in my small
role if anything that if I am able to
just move the needle a little bit in the
National discourses on far less
militancy in this country in the
seriousness that the federal authorities
the local authorities and our
institutions for culture and like you
know pop culture and journalism need to
release see how dangerous it is and we
have elections coming up in 2020 and you
know I shudder to think how this said he
will respond if the elections didn't go
the way they wanted and people you came
here after 2016 but in November here we
had rioting that cost a million dollars
in damage and it was so surreal being in
downtown and seeing masked individuals
run around what about some weapons and
breaking cause destroying properties and
no police and setting fires in the
streets and it was it looked like a war
zone then and unfortunately these
incidents happen with frequency in the
city and I don't know what more needs to
happen for something to change because
as of now everything's remain the same
and how policing works
well I think people who have never seen
civilization breakdown do not understand
what it is that creates safety and
security and so they don't realize how
close we hover to to chaos and what
you're describing is basically the
result of a slight change in the rules
when the mayor starts winking at an tyfa
and letting them know through his
actions that they're going to get away
with most of what they do then they
begin to think about what they might do
and that unfortunately is always the
possibility you know it is the role that
the law and its enforcement plays in
keeping society viable is greater than
we like to think but it's clearly true
and we are beginning to watch it break
down for obviously political reasons and
I hope that your your sacrifice causes
people to rethink this you know what we
don't know
the echo-chamber problem is very serious
what we don't know is how many people
looked at what happened to you people
who naturally would not have ended up
looking at your content and thought wait
a minute
what do I not understand about what's
going on maybe you know this attack does
not what's being said about it doesn't
make any sense
so how many people woke up is the
question as a result of seeing you
attacked in the streets of Portland do
we have any idea do you have a sense
from what you're seeing online about
people having come to their senses as a
result of this I was extremely
appreciative about a 2020 Democratic
presidential candidate Andrew yang
publicly expressed condemnation of what
happened to me
that wasn't just kind it was actually
brave considering the parties that he's
running in and many who on his side who
[Music]
believe all the lies about me I I agree
it shouldn't be courageous but I agree
with you that it is I want to ask you a
couple more questions
I fear bringing up the issue of the
GoFundMe that was set up for you
afterwards because I know that one of
the accusations that will come at you
and is already coming at you is that you
did this for the money right and I've
been on the wrong end of that accusation
so I know how awful it feels when people
say that however I do want to point
something out about it the purpose of
attacking you was to make you and other
journalists too insecure to report the
story the purpose of people deciding to
fund you without you asking them to do
it I mean it was set up by Michelle
Malkin is that right she set up a fund
and you know within a day there was
$100,000 and it is that right something
like that it's completely surreal on the
other hand I think this is actually it's
it's too bad that it comes in the form
of money it really has to given the way
modern society works but what this
really is is a desire to counteract the
attempt to make you very insecure it is
an attempt to make you secure for the
risk that you took and the price that
you've paid and I think it's very
heartening that so many people saw hey
there is something I can do right they
have attacked and you know there's
something I can do to counteract it and
you know the thing about money is at
least it lets you quantify the degree to
which that's a sentiment that everybody
who donated has skin in the game and
they've
said actually you know what you you did
as a service and I see it and so I have
to say I'm I'm thrilled to see the
magnitude of the outpouring and you know
it doesn't compensate you for a head
injury you know head injuries have
serious consequences and that's before
we even get to the psychological impact
of having been attacked and having to
correct your model of the world for that
possibility but anyway I think it's a
very very positive thing how did it make
you feel when you when you discovered
how much people had donated to your
cause it was hard to believe because it
wasn't that long ago that I was just a
Suspiria student journalist writing
basically into the ether you know it
would it would go into print and a
student paper but who read that tweeting
you know - nobody reading my tweets and
that wasn't that long ago and not to
look now like there's so many people out
there supporting me I'm a very
self-critical person unfortunately and
sometimes I get me optically focused on
those bad feeds criticisms on me that
are becoming louder and louder as I've
become more prominent and I forget
there's people who find value in the
work that I do and it's hard to believe
it even when I see it in front of me
through something you can quantify right
like you know something like money
raised these are issues I need to work
on with myself at living in Portland I
am quite persona non grata here so I
don't usually day to day I don't see
real life support it comes primarily
online through messages from people I
don't know so it's harder to visualize
that support as something real because
of
[Music]
but the world is much bigger than
Portland right
the world is much bigger than Portland
and I think what you're getting at there
is a vast group of people in the world
who do not know what to do about this
current situation and they're troubled
by it and they're frightened by it and
when they see somebody do what you did
when they see what I did it evergreen
just standing up and saying no there's
this chorus that comes at you that just
says keep going I don't know how to do I
don't know how to do this in my context
but you do keep going and it does I I
know I shouldn't ask the next question
right it's too soon but I have to ask do
you know what you will do the next time
there's a protest announced in Portland
I think I've heard discussions of some
things being in the early 80s of
planning one of the questions I was
asked today was like something on the
lines of they don t fo succeed in in
stopping you accounting you and I wanted
to say right away no of course not but
with the injury that I'm dealing with
and the changes that I have to make in
the immediate future with how I'm living
my life I'm not able to go in and do the
same things as I do before and that
fear of a mass mobbing happening again
may affect my confidence in wanting to
go in of course I know that now with the
fundraising all that there I have the
resource to to actually source
professional security and all that but
even with professional security what can
you do if there's 30 people coming with
weapons and this conversation has been
focused on me there were other people
injured I didn't witness any of that
that happened after I think I was the
first person who was attacked the crowd
of demonstrators continued to march
towards Pioneer Courthouse Square and
that's where there was fighting and some
of the photos out there the people that
were attacked by an tyfa with weapons
like nunchucks and crowbars and maybe a
brick and a sock these type of things
like in Pioneer Courthouse Square that's
like the heart of downtown Portland
right next to a courthouse and it's like
you see this anarchy and it's this next
thing that I'm gonna say is inflammatory
and I'm gonna say it anyways um Portland
prides itself on being a sanctuary city
but I I see it really as a sanctuary for
violent extremists the mayor in the past
expressed his gratitude to the police
for their restraint in not inciting the
mob and he said this after the elderly
driver was attacked pretty close to
where I was Tech actually last October
and that in that viral footage I'm sure
you seen I sure did i i retweeted that
that was a black lives matter type group
that was a light was an tyfa chased down
this elderly driver and attacked him and
police went there didn't do anything
and the mayor said that was good and so
my only comments to the mayor's you you
know you think that police intervening
is an incitement it's not what what
incites the crowd and what empowers them
actually is inaction from police yeah I
mean this is incredibly simple yeah the
fact is society is based on an agreement
that we don't attack each other in the
street even when we disagree and that
agreement only functions if those who
violate it actually pay a price for
having attacked someone so the answer is
you don't get a choice if you're the
mayor you don't get a choice about
whether or not the law gets enforced it
has to be enforced even if there's a
political price to be paid for it and
you know I would hope mayor wheeler
would follow your courage and the point
is he needs to face whatever political
problem he has with with equal courage
and I I don't expect him to do it but
but it's a requirement we're depending
on that we live in the city of Portland
are depending on the law being enforced
we are depending on blind justice and
the fact that you claim you're on the
Left shouldn't immunize you from it all
right one last question for you it seems
to me that we exist in a special circle
and that special circle as I mentioned
before does not require a person to be
of one political belief or another in
order to be treated humanely and
respected and to have discussion and one
thing I've learned from I would say a
lifetime of talking across political
differences is that it is important that
you seek out that which challenges your
core beliefs even if your core beliefs
are right it's a
that you know what the other sounds like
and not in cartoon terms but in in real
terms so I think you and I very
naturally have no trouble talking to
each other knowing that those
differences exist we can be curious
about what their nature is but they're
not they're not deep I think we agree on
what a just world would look like and
we'd probably don't agree on how close
we are to it or what might be done to
get us further in that direction but my
question to you is how is there any
practical advice for people who may have
thought you a problematic person to use
the parlance now discovering that you're
a human being
navigating a difficult situation with
courage and integrity what can people do
having discovered that there's something
surprising on the other side of a divide
to violate the boundaries of their echo
chamber and discover what exists outside
of it humanizing your ideological
opponents it's very easy particularly
with social media to dehumanize the
other and you know people he's Donald
Trump latina people accuse the right
wing of doing that but you really see it
practice across the board and it's easy
to do it's much easier to be on hating
somebody's ideas or what they believe in
but to also hate them as well having
that person actually become that
physical manifestation of those ideas
and it's it's easier of course to attack
and try to break down a person than to
break down ideas particularly
[Music]
with all the you know I've failed to be
able to convince
antifa militants that I'm a decent human
being I when I was first mobbed by them
in last November in a protest when they
all surrounded me Muslim didn't know who
I was only few them did but those of you
then told everybody a story about who I
was and I was trying to look at them the
ones you know trying to look at them in
their eyes and just be like hey I'm I'm
a normal person you know like and I
couldn't even do that because they were
wearing sunglasses and I felt like I
wasn't even talking to another person I
was regardless of what I said their
response was just anger and hatred and I
was hoping that with my continued
engagement with the group through
attending their events and documenting
things in a completely professional
passive non-confrontational way that
they would see okay we might not like
the way he editorialize is his work when
he's a columnist or we don't like how he
tweets how he chose to or something but
you know he's not a threat to us
unfortunately it went entirely in the
opposite direction of them viewing me as
a threat because of those ideas and
apparently in an existential threat one
that merits this type of response not
just to me but I mean my family's
affected when family personal details
are released out into the public and
these incidents are still lost I was
told being investigated
and it may be like that forever
well I certainly hope that that this
incident marks a turning point that they
do find the people who attack you and
that they deliver justice to them and a
court the way it is supposed to be done
the city of Portland will be much better
off if that happens and it will owe you
a great debt for having exposed the
danger of this cruel and vile movement
in the spirit of what you just said
though I want to be clear it is the
movement that is vile it is the D
individuated mob that is so dangerous we
can't speak about the nature of the
individuals in the movement some of them
are clearly bent on violence some of
them may be rethinking it having seen an
innocent person injured the way you were
only time will tell but it is important
to recognize the danger of the movement
is different than the individuals that
make it up that's important distinction
and thank you for stating that I'm
reminded when one of my video clips of
one of these people confronted me
menacing me went viral an individual who
knew this person from years back
messaged me and gave this person's life
backstory and it was one that was filled
with
mental health struggles in issues with
families and it's unfortunately that
they've chosen to deal with that pain by
manifesting it in in physical rage but
just do those stories this person is no
longer in contact with this person but
it allowed me to see there was a whole
different person behind that mask well
behind the partial mouth up enough of
the face was exposed this is a person
recognize them the story that I you know
would never known and would never be
broadcast to the enemy but I don't know
what it has to happen for for change to
occur but I hope that I can play a part
in it well I must say I to an extent
have chills at the moment this matches
exactly who I've known you to be since
I've come to know who you are over the
last couple years and the fact that even
now sitting there with very visible
injuries and ongoing serious health
consequences from this attack you're
still able to see that there are humans
amongst the mob and that's that's the
important thing
hopefully it happens on the other side -
all right well thank you so much and you
know for doing this I know you have got
to be absolutely exhausted after what
you've been through and I know you
missed one day of sleep probably you're
running on a serious sleep deficit I can
tell people your twitter handle is mr.
Andy no and Gio is that right yes where
else can people look for you
my twitter has the most up-to-date
information on my work so they are
published and from there if you if you
find what I do have value and you want
to support me there are links to
subscribe storm in patreon and some
other options so and there's also the
GoFundMe set up by michelle malkin which
you can go to her Twitter and find that
and maybe that that about does it for my
part let me say this has been an honor
I'm very pleased to have had Andy here
and if you like this content like
subscribe hit the notification button
and I would love to have you back some
point if you're willing it wouldn't be
an honor all right excellent
[Music]
[Applause]